Edwin Swillinger Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edwin Swillinger Papers 1945-2021 1945-1954
MSS86451
Swillinger, Edwin, 1927-2012
350 items
1 containers
0.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Army medic. Correspondence, photographs, and ephemera primarily relating to Swillinger's service during the Allied occupation of Japan between 1946 and 1948.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Edwin Swillinger were given to the Library of Congress by Heidi Swillinger, Timothy Swillinger, and Rebecca Shelley in 2021.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edwin Swillinger are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1927, Aug. 11 Born, Cincinnati, Ohio
1946 Enlisted, U.S. Army
1947 Technician Fifth Grade, 118th Station Hospital, United States Army, Fukuoka, Japan
1948 Honorably discharged, United States Army
1952 B.S., University of Cincinnati, Ohio
1954 M.D., University of Cincinnati, Ohio Married Margery Stephenson (died 1997)
circa 2003 Married Rose Marie Hartman Weishaupt (later divorced)
2012, Aug. 19 Died, Stockton, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edwin Swillinger span the years 1945 to 2021, with the bulk of the material dating from 1945 to 1954. The collection documents Swillinger's service as a medic in the United States Army during the Allied occupation of Japan following World War II. The collection consists primarily of photographs and military ephemera, such as camp newsletters, meal tickets, and Selective Service orders, taken from a scrapbook kept by Swillinger to document his military service and that of his twin brother, Richard Swillinger. Photographs are mainly candid and depict primarily military personnel and installations in the United States and Japan, including images of Nagasaki, Japan, in 1946 showing the aftereffects of the atomic bomb on the landscape. Material not part of the scrapbook consists of photocopies of letters written by Swillinger to his then-girlfriend Rose Marie Hartman, and a 1947 English translation of a 1945 report by Japanese doctors into the effects of radiation on the population of Nagasaki.
Material removed from the scrapbook has been photocopied to promote ease of access and preservation of the originals. Researchers are asked to use the photocopies in lieu of the originals, where available.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Hartman, Rose Marie--Correspondence.; Swillinger, Edwin, 1927-2012.; Swillinger, Richard (Richard Rafael), 1927-2014. Richard Swillinger military records.
Organizations
United States. Army--Foreign service--Japan.; United States. Army--Medical care--Japan.
Subjects
Atomic bomb victims--Japan--Nagasaki-shi.; Atomic bomb--Health aspects.; Atomic bomb--Japan--Blast effect; Atomic bomb--Japan--Nagasaki-shi--Blast effect.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan--Nagasaki-shi.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Places
Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Nagasaki-shi (Japan)--History--Bombardment, 1945.
Occupations
Army medics.; Physicians.
Container List
- 118th Station Hospital, Fukuoka, Japan, miscellany, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Biographical material, circa 1950s, 2010-2012, 2021, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Camp newsletters, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Graduation program, Camp No. 2 Reserve Officers Training Corps, 1953 (Box 1)
- "The Investigation of the Atomic Bomb Disease" (1945) report translation, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Photocopy (Box 1)
  - Original (Box 1)
- Letters to Rose Marie Hartman, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
- Military orders, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Military patches, circa 1947 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Japanese documents, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
- Range scores, circa 1947 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Ration cards and meal tickets, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Scrapbook photocopy, circa 1950s (Box 1)
- Selective Service documents, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Travel documents, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 1)
  - Originals (Box 1)
- Urakami Church, Nagasaki, Japan, postcards, 1947 (Box 1)